<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gophish - Blog</title>
    <link>https://getgophish.com/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gophish - Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 20:05:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://getgophish.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Adding Autocomplete to Gophish</title>
      <link>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/2019-01-02-adding-autocomplete-to-gophish/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 20:05:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/2019-01-02-adding-autocomplete-to-gophish/</guid>
      <description>Gophish provides powerful template tags making it easy to create customized emails and landing pages. Sometimes, however, it can be difficult to remember the exact syntax and what template tags are supported.
I&amp;rsquo;ve had multiple issues filed that are the result of incorrect tags being used. Generally, the crash looks something like this:
worker.go:90: template: html_template:6: function &amp;quot;Name&amp;quot; not defined panic: runtime error: invalid memory address or nil pointer dereference [recovered] panic: runtime error: invalid memory address or nil pointer dereference [signal 0xb code=0x1 addr=0x10 pc=0x61a4a5]  The error from template suggests that a certain function, Name wasn’t defined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Web Servers in Go</title>
      <link>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/2018-12-02-building-web-servers-in-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 16:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/2018-12-02-building-web-servers-in-go/</guid>
      <description>When I first set out to build Gophish 5 years ago, I used it as an opportunity to learn Golang.
One of the things that makes Go so powerful is the batteries-included standard library, which makes it a breeze to write servers. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll walk through how to build web servers, starting from a basic Hello World and ending with a web server that:
 Uses Let&amp;rsquo;s Encrypt for HTTPS Implements an API subrouter Implements middleware Serves static files Shuts down gracefully   If you just want the final code, you can find it in my http-boilerplate repo on Github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handling Database Migrations in Go</title>
      <link>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/database-migrations-in-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 07:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/database-migrations-in-go/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;I got my database schema correct on the first try.&amp;rdquo;
-No one ever.
 Like most big projects, gophish needed a way to automatically manage changes to our database schema. As new features were being added, we found ourselves in a situation that required us to add or modify columns and tables to store the new data.
In a hosted environment, this is no problem since we control the database and can make schema changes as we see fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing gophish v0.1.1</title>
      <link>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/release-0.1.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 06:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/release-0.1.1/</guid>
      <description>Tl;dr - Download the release here
The wait is over! The gophish team is excited to announce our first public beta version of gophish - version 0.1.1! This blog post will be a short introduction into what gophish is, as well as some of the insanely awesome features we&amp;rsquo;ve created.
What is Gophish? Gophish is a phishing framework that makes the simulation of real-world phishing attacks dead-simple. The idea behind gophish is simple – make industry-grade phishing training available to everyone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing gophish</title>
      <link>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 22:05:58 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://getgophish.com/blog/post/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Hello World! This is the official blog for gophish, a phishing toolkit designed to make rock-solid security awareness training accessible to everyone.
Check back here often to find information on gophish updates, how to leverage gophish in interesting ways to test the security of your organization, as well as general tips and tricks on securing your email infrastructure.
The gophish team is excited to release the alpha version of gophish soon!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>